江戸は完全に壊滅してしまうぞ
あんなのが　江戸の端から端まで歩いたら
なかなかだ　去年のやつより狩り甲斐がある
If that thing goes from one
end of Edo to the other,
本字幕由诸神字幕组（kamigami.org）制作，仅供交流学习，禁止用于任何商业用途
日听:东吾 king  翻译:念白白 poopy   校对:木落 时间轴:wcaster
nothing will be left!
Impressive.
I have an even more worthy opponent this year.
Hey, Rikichi...
や　利吉　今日も朝早くから精が出るのぅ
Working hard or hardly working?
おぉ
An earthquake?
地震　また富士のお山が噴火するのか
Is Mt. Fuji about to erupt?
Wh-What is that?
な　なんだありゃ
The forest... The forest is...
森が　樹海が
It's moving?
動いとる
Summer War in Edo!!
「花のお江戸の夏の陣」
Reporting!
報告　只今関八州見回り組より　早馬の知らせが参った
A messenger has just arrived from Kanhasshu.
相州箱根より東海道を下る樹海がある模様
They claim the forest is moving
from Hakone and Soushuu.
Samurai House Patrol
Ogami Kagetada
蟲奉行様
Insect Magistrate...
今年の夏が参りました　城塞級でございます
This year's summer is upon us.
Shrine and Temple Patrol
Murasakama Yumehiki
It is a fortress-class insect.
夏が来たって
So summer's here?
That means tonight is...
ということは　今夜は
そう　夏の風物詩
Yup, the best part of summer...
両国川開き
The Ryougoku River Opening!
川開き　つまり　花火ですか
A river opening?
Is that the fireworks festival?
自分はまだ見たことがなかったんです
I still haven't seen them.
両国花火　楽しみです
The Ryougoku River Opening... I can't wait!
Famous Edo Sights:
Ryougoku River Opening
そうと決まったら　じっとしてられないわね
We'd better get started.
Rejoice, Jinbei.
喜べ　仁兵衛
無知なお前のために　隅田川の川開きの由来を教えてやろう
I shall redress your ignorance
by telling you the origin of the
Sumidagawa River Opening.
そもそもの事の起こりは　慰霊と悪霊を退治する…
It began as a festival of the water god
酒だ　酒持って来い
Sake! Bring me sake!
created by Shogun Tokugawa Yoshimune
承知いたしました
Understood!
to appease the souls of dead
自分で行け　自分で
Go get it yourself.
and drive off evil spirits...
Catching goldfish, candy, pictures, balloons!
金魚掬い　水飴　錦絵　遊山船　それからそれから…
Could it be?
And, and...
Eh?
無視
They're ignoring me?
しかと
ああ　あの家重様　確かに私は毎日いらしても構わないと申しましたが
Um, Ieshige-sama, while I did permit daily visits,
昼日中から彷徨かれましては色々と問題がございますので　できれば…
I didn't mean that you should
loiter here every single day...
ああ　涼しい音色
What a pleasant sound...
Huh?
あれ　風が止んだ
The wind stopped?
季節は夏　草いきれ立ち上り　木々の緑は一層青く
It's summer!
The grass grows high,
the trees grow green,
命が最も盛りを増す頃
and life flourishes everywhere.
この江戸に最強の蟲が現れた
And the ultimate bug appears in Edo!
I suppose summer really is here...
来ましたね　夏が
What is that huge insect?!
おい　与力　なんなのだ　あのバカでかい蟲は
言わずと知れた　カブトムシでございます
The famous rhinoceros beetle.
Masuraou Kabuto
Warrior King Beetle
We call it the Warrior King Beetle.
我らは益荒王兜と呼んでおりますが
If that thing goes from one
end of Edo to the other,
あんなのが　江戸の端から端まで歩いたら
江戸は完全に壊滅してしまうぞ
nothing will be left!
I would imagine so.
でございましょうね
何落ち着いておる　あれを退治するのが蟲奉行所の職務であろう
Why are you so calm?
Isn't it your job
to exterminate those things?
ええ　よく分かっておりますよ
Yes, I am well aware of that.
逃げろ　土の山がこっちに来るぞ
The dust storm is headed this way!
I c-can do it...
僕はできる子
全力突っ張り
Full-Power Slap!
Hydrangea Blossoms.
紫陽花玉
Repentance
懺斬り
Slash!
おお　蟲奉行所のお出番だ
The Insect Magistrate Officers are here!
さあ　ちゃっちゃと片付けるわよ
Now, let's finish this.
戀川殿
Koikawa-dono!
火鉢殿
Hibachi-dono!
天間殿
Tenma-dono...
Where did everyone go?
皆さん　どちらへ行かれたのでしょうか
You're in the way.   Go somewhere safe.
ほら　あんたらは邪魔よ　とっとと避難しなさい
戀川　あんたはそっちの街で逃げ遅れた人がいないか確認してきて
Koikawa, check that no one's
still in the town over there.
人使いが荒いぜ
Why should I listen to you?
天間は皆の避難ルートにある障害物を退かして
Tenma, remove anything that
blocks the evacuation route.
O-Okay.
Huh? Where's Tsukishima?
あれ　そう言えば　月島は
ああ　すっかり忘れてた
I forgot.
What's going on?
なんなのだ　蟲奉行所の者どもは一向に蟲退治をせんではないか
Aren't your officers attacking it at all?
家重様はこれまであまり外に出たことがないので　ご存じないかもしれませんが
You rarely ever stepped outside,
so you may not know this...
夏になると　あのような城塞級の蟲が毎年やってきます
But every summer,
fortress-class insects like that appear.
そんな時我らには　あるルールが適用されます
And when that happens,
we follow a certain rule.
ルールだと
A rule?
はい　無涯君を除くすべての者は町民の避難や退路の確保
Yes.
Everyone but Mugai-kun is to
focus on civilian evacuation,
treating the wounded and ensuring
the escape routes are cleared.
治療その他のサポートに回り
蟲は無涯君一人で退治する
And Mugai-kun takes care
of the insect of himself.
それが蟲奉行所
That is the Insect Magistrate's
Summer War
Summer War.
夏の陣です
なかなかだ　去年のやつより狩り甲斐がある
Impressive.
I have an even more worthy opponent this year.
Um, miss?
あの　そこのお嬢さん　そんなところでどうなさったのです
What are you doing over here?
花火
Fireworks.
Eh?
I'm certain you cannot see
the fireworks from here.
ここからでは　花火は見えぬだろうな
花火でしたら　自分もこれから出かけるところです
I'm actually on my way to
see the fireworks now...
よろしければ　一緒に参りましょう
Would you like to come with me?
That will not happen.
それはかなわぬ
Huh?
わらわはここより出られぬ故
I cannot leave this place.
She can't leave?
出られない
随分高貴なお方のようですが
She appears to be of noble birth...
この蟲奉行所にお勤めしている方の娘さん
Is she the daughter of
someone who works here?
あ　なるほど　ここで親御さんを待っているから　外に出られないんですね
I understand!
You're waiting for your parents,
so you can't leave, right?
Hmm?
先ほどから聞こえるこの地響きは何なんでしょうか
What are all these tremors I keep hearing?
知らぬのか
You don't know?
申し訳ありません　自分は新参者で世間知らずでありまして
I am very sorry!
I only just arrived and there are
many things I do not know.
あれは　花火の試し打ちじゃ
They are just testing the fireworks.
Nothing to worry about.
気にすることはない
そうでしたか　ということは　そろそろ花火が上がるのですね
I see.
Then the fireworks will start soon, right?
これ以上　皆さんを待たせておくわけにはいきません
I can't keep everyone waiting any longer.
では　お嬢さん
Young lady...
Let's find a place within these walls
you can see the fireworks from!
この奉行所から花火が見えるところを　探しましょう
砂塵が舞ってよく見えぬ
The dust clouds are blocking my view.
Do not worry.
ご安心ください　益荒王兜は無涯君がきっと退治してくれます
Mugai-kun will defeat the Warrior King Beetle.
小鳥さん
Kotori-san!
The evacuation is essentially complete.
避難の誘導　あらかた片付いたよ
はい　ご苦労さまです
Glad to hear it.
おい　暴力女
You! Violent girl!
無涯の戦いぶりをもっと近くで見たくはないのか
Don't you want to see Mugai-kun fighting up close?
見たいに決まってるでしょう　これから行こうと思ってたところよ
Of course I do.
I'm about to go.
ならば　俺も連れていけ
Then take me, too!
ああ　家重　いや長福丸　いや
Wait, Ieshige...
何すんだよ
What are you doing?!
Nagatomimaru-sama, no, -kun...
We're way over the weight limit...
もう完璧転移オーバー
触んな　スケベ上役に変質者
Don't touch me, you two perverts!
これも役名です
It's part of my duty.
I am not a pervert!
俺は変質者じゃない
You seem quite proud of this horn.
この角　大層自慢のようだな
それほどのものなら
If it is that wonderful,
この俺が　使ってやってもいい
then I shall make use of it.
仕掛ける気ですね　無涯君
Mugai-kun's about to attack...
やっぱり素敵だわ　無涯さん
Mugai-san really is wonderful.
What about those people over there?
与力よ　それよりも何なのだあいつらは
Are they all insane?
あいつら市井はバカなのか
Why would they hold a party
at a time like this?
こんな時に　何宴会なんぞ開いておるのだ
それは致し方ありません
It can't be helped...
The Insect Magistrate's Summer War
蟲奉行所夏の陣は
両国川開きと並び立つ
大江戸八百八町夏の風物詩ですからね
おい　酒を持ってきてくれねぇ
Hey, bring us some drinks!
is one of Edo's famous summer events,
just like the River Opening.
こっち　食い物ねぇぞ
Do you have any food?
Yes, coming right up!
へい　ただいま
バタバタと薙倒し
Knock it into the ground!
You're in the way! Now I can't see Mugai!
そこ邪魔だ　せっかくの無涯の旦那のお勤めは　見えねぇだろうが
お嬢さん　少しそこでお待ちを
Miss, please wait a second...
只今目一杯花火を楽しむ道具を用意します
I'll find everything we need to enjoy the fireworks!
What are you looking for?
何を探しておる
毛氈です
A carpet.
I can't let someone like you sit on a straw mat!
お嬢さんのようなお方を筵に座らせるわけには参りません
やはり毛氈でなければ
We need a carpet.
コントロールできない
I can't control it!
まさか飛ぶのか
Is it going to jump?
かぶとむしの体の半分は強靭の筋肉
Half a rhinoceros beetle's
body is powerful muscle.
その収縮運動による羽ばたきが
Its rapid contractions cause the wings
to flap, allowing it to fly freely.
巨躯を持ち上げ　自在な飛行を可能にしている
だが　あれは違う
But that is something else!
まさに　その怪力で羽をばたつかせ
It's flapping its wings to create a
powerful dust storm around itself!
全方位に粉塵を大量に撒き散らしているのだ
There's nowhere to run!
あれでは　逃げ場がないぞ
塵外刀　砕の型
Jingaitou:
Rhino Form!
風壁
Wind Barrier!
What?
何っ
無涯のやつ　刀の斬撃で壁を作った
Mugai is using his slashes to make a wall?
砕の型
Rhino Form.
飛水
Flying Water!
存外硬いな
Tougher than expected...
Double Arrow!
二の矢
塵外刀
Jingaitou:
Cascade!
瀑布
すげぇ
やっぱりありませんでした
I couldn't find even one...
他の皆さんが持って行ってしまったのでしょうか
They must have taken all of them.
I found a carpet.
毛氈じゃ見つけて来てやった
これはかたじけない
Thank you so much!
なかなかいい場所が…ありませんね
It's hard to find a good spot...
もうよいぞ
It's fine.
所詮花火などただの気晴らしじゃ
Fireworks are merely a distraction.
あれなどはどうですか
How about there?
蟲見櫓か
The watchtower?
太秦は 神とも神と 聞え来る
"Uzumasa
took his blade and he slew
the greatest of the Eternal Land's gods."
常世の神を　打ち懲ますも
Impossible.
バカな
The katana is absorbing the horn?
刀が角を侵食している
塵外刀　変化
Jingaitou: Transformation.
Attack Form: Rhino!
型式　兜
The Jingaitou Transformation landed!
塵外刀　変化決まった
無涯の旦那の大花道
Mugai wins!
この千両役者
What a show!
お見事　日本一
Splendid! Finest in Japan!
It's begun.
始まったようです　急ぎましょう
Let's hurry!
お手を
Take my hand.
Stop.
止めておけ
No one is allowed to touch me.
わらわに触れることは　何人たりとも許されぬ
Now, let's go.
さ　参りましょう
何と美しい
How beautiful!
それに試しうちの時よりずっと音がよい
And they sound much better
than the preparations.
You'd really never seen them before?
本当に見たことがなかったのか　花火
自分は生まれ故郷から一度も外へ出たことがなかったのです
I'd never even left my homeland.
ですから今日お勤めの仲間からお誘いを受けた時は すっごくうれしかったのです
So when my comrades invited
me today, I was so happy.
Comrades?
仲間…
I'm sorry you couldn't watch with them
残念であったな
because you were trying to help me.
わらわなど気にかけたばかりに
Not at all.
とんでもない
Because of you, I was able to have a great view.
おかげでこのような眺めのよいところで 花火を楽しむことができました
それに　花火を見たい気持ち
And more than anyone,
I know how wanting to see them feels.
自分が一番知っていますから
I shall reward you.
そちに褒美を取らそう
A reward?
褒美
For bringing me this far.
わらわをここまでつれてきてくれた礼じゃ
Give it no thought.
気にするな
ただの安物じゃ
It is a trifle.
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much!
I, Tsukishima Jinbei, will treasure it forever.
この月島仁兵衛　後生大事に致します
Oh...
そうか
そちが月島か
So you are Tsukishima?
Let's finish this off with a bang!
それじゃ最後に一発　ど派手にでかいの
行くわよ
天間
Tenma...
う　うん
R-Right.
いってらっしゃい
Go!
Here's the last one for today!
これにて　本日はお開き
いつの間にか　あんなところに小山ができてる
Since when was there a hill over there?
What is that?
何でしょうか
Huh?
あれ
Well done, Matsunohara Kotori.
大儀であった　松ノ原小鳥
You honor me.
はっ　ありがたきお言葉
さて  あの蟲が現れたということは
Now, then.
That insect's appearance heralds
the arrival of summer.
夏に入ったということ
The insects are acting strangely.
この江戸の蟲のざわつき
今年は何か　今までとは違うように思える
Something is different this year.
It's a little early,
少々早いが
これよりわらわは例年通り
but I shall now seal myself away,
according to the custom.
御籠りに入る
Insect Magistrate
High-Ranking Minister
So you've decided to make you move, huh?
どうやら動き出したようね
さぁ　行くわよ
Let's go.
I'll follow that carriage wherever it goes.
あの駕籠　どこまでも追いかけてやるわ
Next Time
Once they see this hot body,
any guy will do whatever I say!
私のナイスボディーを見せ付ければ
次回予告
どんな男も思いのままよ
The guy over there looks nice and stupid.
あら　あんなところにバカ正直そうなやつ
Come on, Samurai-sama, let's play.
そこのお侍様　遊びましょう
Next time, on Mushibugyou:
次回　蟲奉行「蜜月のお色気?大作戦」
Mitsuki's Honey Trap.
Mitsuki's Honey                  Trap
What? You're ignoring me?!
ちょっと　しかと？